Vivekpandian Veerapandian

Sunnyvale, CA (214) 802-4843 website: v github.com/vivekpandian08 linkedin.co

website: vivekpandian08.github.io linkedin.com/in/vivekpandian8

vivekpandian08@gmail.com medium.com/@vivekpandian08

Data Scientist with **3-years of experience** in extracting customer and marketing insights from data points by building Linear and Non-Linear ML models. Proficient at framing ETL pipeline and deploying end-to-end machine learning models in the Cloud.

EDUCATION

M.S., Data Science and Business Analytics , The University of Texas at Dallas

GPA: 3.67

Jan 2019 - Dec 2020

- Project Mentor, BALC: Mentored 15 Grad Students in an Intra College ML project competition, and secured 3rd place
- Coursework: Statistics, Predictive Analytics, Econometrics, Time Series Forecasting, Machine Learning, Google Analytics

B.E., Electronics and Communication, College of Engineering Guindy, India

Aug 2007 – May 2011

SKILLS

Programming: Python (Scikit-learn, Pandas, Numpy, TensorFlow, PyTorch, Keras, OpenCV, PySpark), R, SQL, SAS

Data Visualization : Tableau, Power BI, Shiny, GGPlot2, Plotly, Matplotlib, Seaborn, Bokeh

Databases & Bigdata : Big Query, MySQL, PostgreSQL, Oracle, Graph, MongoDB (NoSQL), Hadoop, Hive, Spark

ML Concepts : Hypothesis Testing, A/B Testing, Regression, Classification, Clustering, NLP, Computer Vision

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Senior Data Scientist Tech: Python, R, Tableau, AWS EC2, S3

Jan 2015 - June 2018

Ordermycake, India – E-Commerce B2C Platform to sell Bakery Products

- Generated **18% increase in revenue to \$5k** in 2017 by leveraging sentiment analysis, extracting topics and key phrases on customers feedback, and suggested a new payment method to solve delivery problems
- Designed 3 A/B tests to identify the most engaging marketing campaign, resulted in a 30% increase in sales
- Identified 4500 potential churn customers by developing ML models and mitigated 36% by offering them discounts
- Revamped coupon mailing strategy for 3 customer segments by clustering using **K-means** and identifying the most engaging coupons leading to a **12% estimated increase in headcount**
- Recommended optimized price for products by web scraping and data mining to analyze competitor product prices, leading to a \$3K increase in yearly revenue
- Led a 10-member cross-functional team to build an end to end B2C platform to expand the operations from 2 to 8 cities

Software Engineer

Tech: MySQL, C

Mar 2012 – Sept 2014

Cluster Wireless Software, India – Developed Software which facilitates M2M communications through IoT applications

- Designed SQL queries to extract information from IoT sensor data and identified anomalies by K-means clustering
- Analyzed product pain points and collaborated with a multi-functional team to develop robust solutions to meet client requirements, increased project conversion to 30%

INTERNSHIP EXPERIENCE

Data Science Intern Tech: R, Python

Sept 2020 - Present

SuperWorld, United States – Augmented Reality Real Estate on Blockchain

• Built **Predictive model** using Decision Tree to find the likelihood of a purchase from clickstream data and optimize the model by adding new features to improve the precision rate to 76%

PERSONAL PROJECTS (DATA SCIENCE)

Stress Detection on Social Media

Python (Natural Language Processing)

- Leveraged web scrapping to scrape 30k labeled Reddit posts and extracted features by pre-training Word2Vec, Doc2Vec and BERT embeddings with 190k unlabeled posts that capture semantic and syntactic similarity among words
- Trained XGBoost and BERT models to classify Stress posts on GCP, that achieved accuracy of 92.74% and recall of 94.58%

Traffic Sign Recognition for Autonomous Driving

Python (Computer Vision)

- Pre-processed images and experimented with 5 different CNN architectures using Tensorflow to classify 43 traffic signs
- Deployed an interactive web APP that classifies traffic sign from user input using Flask(REST API) and Kubernetes on GCP

Credit Card Fraud Detection

Python (Supervised Learning)

• Performed data analysis, and hypothesis testing. Built an **ML pipeline** using **python(PySpark)** to predict fraud transaction using SVM, KNN, Naïve Bayes, Random Forest, and Neural Networks with **SMOTE** resampling and achieved AUC of 0.82